A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Board of Nursing, 1903-1984 (bulk 1903-1970)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Board of Nursing, 1903-1984 (bulk 1903-1970)
The Library of Virginia
43495
1.6 cu. ft. (4 boxes)
Virginia Board of Nursing
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Maureen Spokes, Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry, University of Virginia School of Nursing, McLeod Hall, P.O. Box 800782, Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, 19 October 2007.
Custodial History
The provenance of this collection is not entirely clear. Before arriving at the Library of Virginia, the collection was housed at the Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry at the University of Virginia School of Nursing. From whom the papers were initially received remains unknown.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia General Assembly created the State Board of Examiners of Graduate Nurses with the enactment of the Nurse Practice Act in 1903. The purpose of the regulation of nursing by the state was to protect the health and welfare of Virginia's citizenry. The act provided a way to regulate the nursing profession, as well as provide a means to inspect Virginia's many nurse training schools. The Board was responsible for administering the certification examination, first held in Richmond in 1904. The first formal criteria used during school inspections was developed in 1905. A certification process for licensed attendants was added in 1918. Certified tuberculosis nurses were regulated beginning in 1926, and an amendment to the Nurse Practice Act established the regulation of licensed practical nurses in 1946. The categories of clinical nurse specialist, certified nurse aide, and massage therapist were added in later years.
The board has been subject to several name changes since its inception. It began as the "State Board of Examiners of Graduate Nurses" in 1903, but later became the "State Board of Examiners of Nurses" in 1946. In 1970, the name was changed to the "Virginia State Board of Nursing," and in 1989 it was again changed to the "Virginia Board of Nursing."
Members of the Virginia Board of Nursing are appointed by the Governor to four-year terms. The Board began with five registered nurses, but is now composed of thirteen members. Two important figures featured in this collection are Julia Mellichamp and Ethel Smith, who both served as Secretary-Treasurer of the Board during the first half of the 20th century. Mellichamp was the first to serve in this paid position beginning in 1914 and ending in 1920, while Smith served as Secretary-Treasurer and also as Inspector of Training Schools from 1920 to 1937.
The Board is now part of the Virginia Department of Health Professions. The Department of Health Regulatory Boards was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 31, 1977, to provide administrative services to the health regulatory boards of the state. In 1986, the Department of Health Regulatory Boards was renamed the Department of Health Professions.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence, minutes, reports, law and policy information, and a variety of material associated with nursing organizations on the state and national levels. The bulk of the collection dates before 1970, though there are a few scattered documents from later years. For the most part, the collection is comprised of records from when the Board was known as the State Board of Examiners of Graduate Nurses (prior to 1946), and as the Board of Examiners of Nurses (1946-1970). Files of note include those devoted to Ethel Smith, long-time Secretary-Treasurer of the Board, as well as the correspondence of Julia Mellichamp in her capacity as Secretary-Treasurer. Files containing various reports of the Board, meeting minutes, and the annual reports of the nurse training schools provide detailed information on the Board and its activities. This collection provides an early glimpse into the realm of professional nursing in Virginia.
Contents List
- Series I. Records, 1903-1984 (bulk 1903-1970).
  - "A Trip through the Human Body," undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounting Audits, 1920-1923. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Act to Regulate the Professional Nursing of the Sick in the State of Virginia, 1903-1921. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amendments to the Nurse Practice Act in Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Nurses' Association, 1918-circa 1960. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Nurses' Association: Report of the Conference of Representatives of State Boards of Nurse Examiners, 1943. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Nurses' Association: Report of the Conference of State Boards of Nurse Examiners, 1947. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Lynchburg Hospital), 1931-1940. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Medical College of Virginia), 1929-1939. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Riverside Hospital), 1927. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (St. Elizabeth's Hospital), 1928-1934. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (St. Elizabeth's Hospital), 1936-1942. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (St. Luke's Hospital), 1929-1932. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Stuart Circle Hospital), 1931-1933. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Virginia Baptist Hospital), 1924-1933. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual Reports: Training School for Nurses (Virginia Baptist Hospital), 1936-1939. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1942-1971. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Certificates, 1916. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (General), 1905-1919. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1911-1914. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1915-1916. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1917-1918. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1919. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1920. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Mellichamp, Julia), 1925-1938. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Smith, Ethel), 1927-1934. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Essentials of a Good School of Nursing," 1936. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Examination Questions, 1914-1915. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finanicial Records, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Governor's Committee on Nursing: "Nursing in Virginia" (Final Report), 1969. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Nurses' Association of Virginia: Certificate of Incorporation, 1914. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Nurses' Association of Virginia: Constitution and By-Laws, 1914-1927. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Nurses' Association of Virginia: Reports to the, 1918-1919. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Law and By-Laws Governing the Registration and Examination of Nurses, 1917. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Laws and By-Laws Governing the Registration and Examination of Nurses and Licensed Attendants in Virginia, 1927-1932. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Laws and By-Laws Governing the Registration and Examination of Nurses and Licensed Attendants in Virginia, 1941-1945. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Law Governing the Registration and Examination of Graduate Nurses, Certified Tuberculosis Nurses, Practical Nurses and Licensed Attendants in Virginia, 1946-1951. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Law Governing the Examination, Licensure and Practice of Professional Nurses, Certified Tuberculosis Nurses, Practical Nurses and Licensed Attendants, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Licensed Attendants (World War I Nurse Shortage), 1918-1919. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - List of Accredited Schools of Nursing, 1926. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1914-1915. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1917. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1918-1920. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Montgomery, Mabel, 1971-1984. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National League for Nursing: Early Nursing Source Material, 1954-1958. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National League of Nursing Education: Pamphlets, 1933. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National League of Nursing Education: Report for the Advisory Council Meeting, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National League of Nursing Education: "Suggested Minimum Qualifications of Personnel for Nursing Schools and Hospital Nursing Services," undated. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nursing Brochures, 1951-1960. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photograph (Identified), 1903. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Policies, Regulations and Recommendations for the Accreditation of Virginia Schools of Nursing, 1951. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Registered Nurse (Definition of), undated. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Resolution, undated. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Richmond Nurses' Club: Constitution and By-Laws, undated. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Roster of Nurses Licensed for Active Practice in Virginia, 1954. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Rules and Qualifications for Student Nurses, undated. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rulings of the Virginia State Board of Examiners of Nurses, 1947. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - School Inspection Questionnaires, 1918; undated. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Smith, Ethel, 1923-1948. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Ethel, 1923-1948. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Smith, Ethel, 1923-1948. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Southern States Rating Grading Comm. (First Report), undated. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Teaching and Testing Material, undated. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Teaching and Testing Material, undated. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Tidewater League for Nursing: By-Laws and Meeting Material, 1963-1965. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Tidewater League for Nursing: Newsletters, 1964-1965. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Tidewater League for Nursing / Norfolk League for Nursing: Correspondence, 1963-1964. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Virginia League for Nursing: Committee on Historical Source Materials, 1965-1970. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Virginia League for Nursing: Meeting Material, 1969-1970. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Virginia League of Nursing Education: Correspondence, 1940. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Virginia League of Nursing Education: Meeting Material, 1938-1939. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Virginia League of Nursing Education: Meeting Material, 1940-1942. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Virginia League of Nursing Education: Programs, 1938-1941. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Virginia State League of Nursing Education: By-Laws, undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Virginia State League of Nursing Education: Miscellaneous Material, undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Virginia State League of Nursing Education: State League Portfolio, undated. (Box 4, Folder 9)